Hey everybody, in this last content
video for going over pandas,
we're going to talk about handling
messy data. So one of the reasons
that I like the Titanic data set
is that it's not perfect. And
I think more often than not in
life, you have data sets that don't
completely accurately reflect
reality. I mean, if I took a survey
of our current class and asked
you, I don't know, something that
there's definitely a clear answer
to, like your height, maybe,
then we would hope that we'd get 100
% accuracy on a survey such as that.
But just because I ask you a question
doesn't mean you have to answer
honestly, or doesn't mean that maybe
you're feeling silly and you want
to put down a silly answer,
something like that, right? There's a
million reasons why data isn't
accurately entered. But what we have to
realize as data scientists and data
analysts is that we're often pretty
much 100% of the time working with
data that's not perfect. And so this
isn't going to be a comprehensive
way of how to handle messy data, but
we're just going to talk about some
of the ways that we can handle it
in Python using Pandas. So we've
got the Titanic data set again, I've
already loaded it in. And what I
want to do is I want to see how many
values I have that aren't numbers.
I'm going to use is NA so not a number
or NA it stands for something but
and just that's the function we'll
use. So is NA so not a value we want
to count those up. So you can see
I've got values in all of my rows
and columns except for age, I have
177 missing values, Cab and I have
687 missing values, and Embarked, I
have two missing values. So one of
the things that we can do is we can
drop our NAs from our data frame.
So So here's a, let's print out, and
then what we'll do is we will
clean, clean our NA vowels.
We'll set that equal to dataframe
.dropNA, and that's a function
you can use. And then let's print
out the shape after cleaning.
We'll just do dataframe.shape,
and note the difference here.
okay so oh something didn't happen
let's go they printed out the data
frame again instead of the clean
one so clean NA vowels here we go
okay so our original shape was 891
rows 12 columns and after we clean
we have 183 values and 12 columns
or rows and columns so is is it
worth it to drop any values in this
case? Probably not because we lose
such a staggering amount of our
data here. So maybe a smarter way
to do things would be to target
specific columns. So for example,
we're missing only two values in the
embarked column. So maybe one thing
I could do is I could say embarked
clean is equal to data frame dot
drop na and then let's do a subset
here we only want to drop our
embarked column and then let's print
out the embarked clean dot shape
okay so 12 columns 888 or 889
rows is a lot better than 183 so
this is pretty good um but what
about all of our other data that's
still missing right like we're
missing cabin numbers for most
everybody so it kind of begs the
question of what do we do like is
cabin number really really important
to our analysis? Is it something
that's going to play into maybe
a machine learning algorithm?
Maybe, maybe not. But what we
don't want to have is a bunch of
missing values. And so there's a
couple things that we can do. So I'm
going to add a new code cell in
here. And maybe let's fill in some
of this missing data. So let's
look again, we've got age that's
missing a bunch, cabin that's missing
a bunch, and embarked. So we took
care of embarked, we dropped
those, let's maybe tackle age next.
So let's
print out missing ages before.
Let's say data frame at age.
We'll say
is NA and we'll do a sum of that.
And then what we'll do
is it can be common to
include or when cleaning
values, you can add in the
average age to fill all
of our missing values.
That can sometimes be skewed by
outliers, so another good practice
is to fill missing values with
the median age instead. So
in order to find the median age,
and that's what we'll do here,
median age we'll say is our
data frame in our age column,
and then you probably guessed it,
there's literally just a a function
median and then what we'll do and
let's actually print out what that is
median age
and then let's fill our
our column with that
so let's actually make
a new column we'll say
data frame age filled
and we will set that equal to data frame
at our age column and then we'll
use another function called fill
NA which is super fun and we'll
fill it with the median age and this
is actually something I don't
think we've talked about up to this
point is that you can create new
columns in a data frame and it's
as easy as just saying the name of
data frame creating a bracket and
then um making a new column so we
could we could make as many new
columns as we want it's kind of
like adding something to the end of
a list we can continue adding and
adding and adding um and it can
be beneficial especially if we have
new items that we want to add on
to our data frame that are a
byproduct of other columns so for
example if I had um maybe like profit
and or not profit uh how do you
calculate like a actually my mind
is blanking on that but maybe if
I had like sales and tax then maybe
I'd calculate like sales tax or
something in a new column so bad
example we filled our ages now so
let's do another print statement
here ages after or missing ages
after I guess and we'll print out
the data frame at our new column,
age filled, is an A dot, oh my gosh,
awesome.
Okay, that took a minute.
So we'll run this cell block,
and of course I made a mistake.
There we go. Okay, so our missing
age before was 177. We filled in all
the missing ages with 28, it looks
like, and then we have no missing
ages after. So this is a great tool
we can use. And at this point, we
could now drop the age column, but
it's still a bit valuable data. And
we don't ever want to completely
just, so like now that we've filled
in the missing ages, that's something
that we should very, very clearly
communicate to whoever our findings
are going towards. if I was doing
some kind of an analysis on this
and I was reporting the findings of
that analysis to higher ups or
somebody who's really interested in
the Titanic I would want to be very
very clear that I filled in missing
age values with the median age okay
so just another quick thing there
okay and our last one that was
missing was our cabin number and
so what we can do here is something
maybe a little bit different.
Let's label all missing
cabins as unknown.
Let me add a little bit
of documentation here.
I forgot to fill missing
pages with median page.
I also forgot to add
documentation here. Let me do that
really quick as well. we will
drop missing and embarked.
Okay, so label all missing cabins
as unknown. So let's take our data
frame at our cabin spot, and we'll
say data frame at cabin dot fill
na with unknown and then let's
just output our data frame at cabin
and we'll see what it gives us
okay so that looks pretty good so
unknown ca5 unknown and it looks
like we've got quite a few unknowns,
which we expected. So to sum up,
there's a lot of ways you can handle
missing data. This is by no means
the only way, nor is it a perfect
way. And when we deal with missing
data or get rid of missing data,
we need to be very, very clear
and explicit with our audience or
whoever we're sharing our findings
with that that is what we're doing.
So that there's no kind of like, so
we're having transparency, right?
Like the worst thing is when somebody
takes data and skews it so that
they're trying to give you reporting
their findings that are accurate
to the data and you guys are data
stewards because you're studying
at least this class with regards to
data analysis so it's important to
be very open and clear about the
data that you're using that's going
to sum up everything for this content
video, so thanks for watching.